{"tossups": [{"question": "A replica of this structure in Alliance, Nebraska was made from cars spray-painted grey. Early construction at this site included a round ditch and pits known as Aubrey holes. The material for this structure may have been quarried in Marlborough Downs or Wales. The sarsen trilithons that make up the outer ring of this structure were built using mortise and tenon joints, and they align with the sun during the summer and winter solstice. For ten points, name this Neolithic structure on Salisbury Plain in Southern England.", "answer": "<b> Stonehenge</b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "In this war, Hanover was forced to withdraw after the Convention of Klosterzeven, then re-entered after the Battle of Rossbach. The Diplomatic Revolution led to the setup of this war\u2019s alliances. This war was motivated in part by an Austrian desire to recover Silesia. It began with an invasion of Saxony and ended with the Treaty of Paris between Britain and France. For ten points, name this global war between European powers that ended in 1763, often considered the first \u201cWorld War\u201d for its theaters in North America and India.", "answer": "<b> Seven Years</b>\u2019 War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This man is in the center of a mosaic in the Basilica of San Vitale in Ravenna, which was conquered by the man to his right in that mosaic. The first appearance of<em> Yersinia pestis</em> in Europe occurred during a plague named for this man. Belisarius conquered the Vandals for this ruler, whose reign was described in Procopius\u2019s<em> Secret History</em>. The Nika Riots opposed this husband of Theodora. For ten points, name this Byzantine emperor who published a law code in 529 AD.", "answer": "<b> Justinian</b> I (or<b> Justinian</b> the Great)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Paul Rothemund of Caltech initiated the practice of using this material for origami. Its function was demonstrated through the use of sulfur and phosphorous to label bacteriophages in a 1952 experiment performed by Hershey and Chase. This molecule\u2019s structure was determined with the aid of X-ray diffraction images taken by Rosalind Franklin. For ten points, name this molecule whose double-helix structure was determined by Watson and Crick and that carries our genetic code.", "answer": "<b> Deoxyribonucleic acid</b> or<b> DNA</b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {}, {"question": "Into the early 20th century, these people had to undergo privy examinations to be sure they were of sound mind to sell their property. The legal doctrine of coverture removed legal rights, such as the right to enter contracts, from these people, and these people were not allowed to apply for credit cards until 1974. The Cult of Domesticity detailed proper values for, for ten points, what class of people whose votes were claimed by anti-suffragists to merely double or negate those of their husbands?", "answer": "(married)<b> women</b> (accept equivalents, such as<b> wives</b>,<b> girls</b>, etc.)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "In 1953, Tenzing Norgay and Sir Edmund Hillary became the first people to accomplish, for ten points, what feat of conquering the tallest peak in the Himalayas?", "answer": "<b> climb</b>ing Mount<b> Everest</b> (or descriptions of<b> summit</b>ting or<b> reaching the top of</b> Mount <b>Everest</b>)", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "This man died at Otrar while planning an invasion of Ming China. This man\u2019s corpse was exhumed just before Operation Barbarossa by Soviet anthropologists. He began his rise to power from Transoxiana, and his descendant Ulugh Beg built an observatory in this man\u2019s capital city. He constantly came into conflict with the Chagatai Khanate, won the Battle of Ankara, and executed Bayezid I. For ten points, name this legendary builder of skull pyramids, a crippled Mongol who conquered a huge empire based in Samarkand.", "answer": "<b> Timur</b> the Lame (or<b> Tamerlane</b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This organization ran the Addiscombe College for prospective officers in the Presidency armies. This organization was opposed by governors called Polygars. This organization was opposed by Tipu Sultan, who fought four Mysore Wars against it. Its ascent to power began after Robert Clive won the Battle of Plassey against the Nawab of Bengal, who had orchestrated the Black Hole of Calcutta. For ten points, name this joint stock company that conquered most of the Indian subcontinent for England.", "answer": "<b> British East India</b> Company (prompt on \u201cEast India Company\u201d alone)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "\u201d Frederic Bartholdi designed, for ten points, what green-hued statue in New York Harbor?", "answer": "<b> Statue of Liberty</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "Adolphe Thiers\u2019 [tee-ayrz] desire to establish this river as a border led to an 1840 crisis. A bridge over this river at Remagen was notably captured intact by American forces during World War II. Operation Market Garden was a failed attempt to cross this river, which passes by the heavily industrialized Ruhr region. A capital city on this river was Bonn, and this river served with the Danube as the northern border of the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this prominent river in western Germany.", "answer": "<b> Rhine</b> River", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "This man was Commanding General of the US Army during the Nez Perce War and the Great Sioux War. During one campaign, he constantly outflanked Joseph Johnston and decisively defeated John Bell Hood. This man\u2019s soldiers twisted train tracks around trees to create his namesake neckties as part of his strategy of \u201chard war.\u201d For ten points, name this Civil War general, a lieutenant of Ulysses Grant, who presented Savannah to President Lincoln for a Christmas gift and burned Atlanta during his March to the Sea.", "answer": "William Tecumseh<b> Sherman</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "For ten points, name this country that was ruled by the Habsburgs, joined in a Dual Monarchy with Hungary, and hosted the Congress of Vienna.", "answer": "<b> Austria</b> (or<b> Osterreich</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This program required the creation of the Persian Corridor into Azerbaijan. This program, which effectively nullified the Neutrality Acts, was preceded by a system of</b> <b>(+)</b> <b>trading destroyers for bases and replaced the \u201ccash and carry\u201d system once British</b> <b>money ran out. Franklin Roosevelt\u2019s announcement that the United States would be the (*)</b>\u201cArsenal of Democracy\u201d promoted, for ten points, what American aid program the supplied the Allies with war materiel and loans in exchange for American use of military bases?", "answer": "<b> Lend-Lease</b> Act (or Bill or Law; accept descriptive answers that describe American<b> lend</b>ing and<b> lease</b>s of military bases)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>The final place of employment for this novel\u2019s protagonist is at Tommy Hind\u2019s hotel. A boy in this novel drowns in a puddle of dirty water after his teenage mother Ona dies in</b> <b>childbirth. The phrase (+)</b> <b>\u201cChicago will be ours!\u201d is chanted at a socialist rally attended</b> <b>by the Lithuanian immigrant Jurgis Rudkus at this novel\u2019s conclusion. The 1906 Pure (*) </b>Food and Drug Act was passed in response to, for ten points, what novel about the Chicago meatpacking industry, written by Upton Sinclair?", "answer": "The<b> Jungle</b>", "metadata": "Literature - American Literature - Long Fiction"}, {"question": "<b>As Home Secretary, this politician successfully appealed the European Court of Human Rights\u2019 decision to prevent Abu Qatada from being deported. Shortly after this leader took office, the Department of Energy and Climate Change was abolished. This leader has said that (+) Article 50 of the Lisbon Treaty will not be invoked in 2016, despite a referendum held calling for her country to (*)</b> leave the EU. For ten points, name this current Prime Minister of the United Kingdom, the second woman to hold that position.", "answer": "Theresa<b> May</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b>This man\u2019s forces were betrayed on a journey to Messina by his hired Cilician pirates; shortly after, he was denied a truce, then decisively beaten and killed at the Siler (+) River. A single man volunteered to lead an army to defeat this former</b><em><b> murmillo</b></em><b>; the practice of killing every tenth soldier, or decimation, was reintroduced for discipline purposes by that volunteer, (*) </b> Crassus. After this leader lost the Third Servile War, his followers were crucified along the Appian Way. For ten points, name this first century BC Greek soldier who led a failed slave revolt after escaping captivity as a Roman gladiator.", "answer": "<b> Spartacus</b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b>This man lived in exile for several years in a Novotel Hotel, where he was interviewed by Brian Barron. This ruler allowed Air France Flight 139 to land in his nation, leading (+) Israel to retaliate with Operation Entebbe. This ally of Muammar Gaddafi and former officer of the King\u2019s African Rifles declared himself King of (*)</b> Scotland and forced all Asians in his country to leave, but was overthrown after a failed attempt to annex Kagara from Tanzania. For ten points, name this eccentric Ugandan dictator during the 1970s.", "answer": "<b> Idi Amin</b> Dada", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b>Henry Lawton\u2019s 2nd Division was unable to reach this battle in time because they were held up at the Battle of El Caney. At this battle, troops under Jacob Kent and Samuel Sumner were subjected to deadly Mauser fire while waiting for Lawton in an area known</b> <b>as (+)</b> <b>Hell\u2019s Pocket or Bloody Ford. The 10th Cavalry Buffalo Soldiers was the only unit</b> <b>to assault both the stronghold that names this battle and its lower counterpart, (*)</b> Kettle Hill. For ten points, name this July 1st, 1898 battle in which Teddy Roosevelt led a charge of the Rough Riders during the Spanish-American War.", "answer": "Battle of<b> San Juan Hill</b> (or<b> San Juan Heights</b>; do not prompt on San Juan alone)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b>The Boston police threatened this person with a $100 fine for using a dominant seventh chord in his arrangement of</b><em><b> The Star-Spangled Banner</b></em><b>. Allied victory in World War II inspired the coda of this composer\u2019s</b><em><b> Symphony in Three Movements</b></em><b>, and a dissonant chord</b> <b>represents the title (+)</b> <b>puppet in a ballet he wrote for Serge Diaghilev\u2019s Ballet Russes.</b> <b>Another piece by this composer of</b><em><b> Petrushka</b></em><b>, in which a young girl dances herself to death in a sacrificial rite, (*)</b> caused a riot at its 1913 premiere. For ten points, name this Russian composer of the<em> Rite of Spring</em>.", "answer": "Igor Fyodorovich<b> Stravinsky</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}], "bonuses": []}